Tufts Published Scholarship PB
Tufts Archival Research Center
- Perseus Project Publications, 1987 -- 2014; PB.001; 56 Digital Object(s)
  - Guidelines for the Syntactic Annotation of Latin Treebanks (v. 1. 3), 2007; PB.001.002.00006; Bamman, David; Crane, Gregory; Passarotti, Marco; Raynaud, Savina
    Treebanks; Latin language; Natural language processing; Latin language-data processing; Latin language-syntax; Digital libraries; Perseus Project
  - Transferring Structural Markup Across Translations Using Multilingual Alignment and Projection, 2010; PB.001.002.00007; Bamman, David; Crane, Gregory; Babeu, Alison
    We present here a method for automatically projecting structural information across translations, including canonical citation structure (such as chapters and sections), speaker information, quotations, markup for people and places, and any other element in TEI-compliant XML that delimits spans of text that are linguistically symmetrical in two languages. We evaluate this technique on two datasets, one containing perfectly transcribed texts and one containing errorful OCR, and achieve an accuracy rate of 88.2% projecting 13,023 XML tags from source documents to their transcribed translations, with an 83.6% accuracy rate when projecting to texts containing uncorrected OCR. This approach has the potential to allow a highly granular multilingual digital library to be bootstrapped by applying the knowledge contained in a small, heavily curated collection to a much larger but unstructured one.
    Digital libraries; Annotation projection; Multilingual alignment; Knowledge transfer; Perseus Project
  - An Ownership Model of Annotation: The Ancient Greek Dependency Treebank, 2009; PB.001.002.00008; Bamman, David; Mambrini, Francesco; Crane, Gregory
    We describe here the first release of the Ancient Greek Dependency Treebank (AGDT), a 90,903-word syntactically annotated corpus of literary texts including the works of Hesiod, Homer and Aeschylus. hile the far larger works of Hesiod and Homer (142,705 words) have been annotated under a standard reebank production method of soliciting annotations from two independent reviewers and then econciling their differences, we also put forth with Aeschylus (48,198 words) a new model of treebank roduction that draws on the methods of classical philology to take into account the personal responsibility of the annotator in the publication and ownership of a "scholarly" treebank.
    Digital libraries; Treebanks; Perseus Project
  - Structured Knowledge for Low-Resource Languages: The Latin and Ancient Greek Dependency Treebanks, 2009; PB.001.002.00009; Bamman, David; Crane, Gregory
    We describe here our work in creating treebanks -- large collections of syntactically annotated data -- for Latin and Ancient Greek. While the treebanks themselves present important datasets for traditional research in philology and linguistics, the layers of structured knowledge they contain (including disambiguated lemma, morphological, and syntactic information for every word) help offset the comparatively small size of extant Greek and Latin texts for text mining applications. We describe two such uses for these Classical treebanks -- discovering lexical knowledge from a large corpus with the help of a small treebank, and identifying patterns of text reuse.
    Treebanks; Text mining; Perseus Project
  - The Latin and Ancient Greek Dependency Treebanks, 2011; PB.001.002.00010; Bamman, David; Crane, Gregory
    This paper describes the development, composition, and several uses of the Ancient Greek and Latin Dependency Treebanks, large collections of Classical texts in which the syntactic, morphological and lexical information for each word is made explicit. To date, over 200 individuals from around the world have collaborated to annotate over 350,000 words, including the entirety of Homer's Iliad and Odyssey, Sophocles Ajax, all of the extant works of Hesiod and Aeschylus, and selections from Caesar, Cicero, Jerome, Ovid, Petronius, Propertius, Sallust and Vergil. While perhaps the most straightforward value of such an annotated corpus for Classical philology is the morphosyntactic searching it makes possible, it also enables a large number of downstream tasks as well, such as inducing the syntactic behavior of lexemes and automatically identifying similar passages between texts.
  - Measuring Historical Word Sense Variation, 2011; PB.001.002.00011; Bamman, David; Crane, Gregory
    We describe here a method for automatically identifying word sense variation in a dated collection of historical books in a large digital library. By leveraging a small set of known translation book pairs to induce a bilingual sense inventory and labeled training data for a WSD classifier, we are able to automatically classify the Latin word senses in a 389 million word corpus and track the rise and fall of those senses over a span of two thousand years. We evaluate the performance of seven different classifiers both in a tenfold test on 83,892 words from the aligned parallel corpus and on a smaller, manually annotated sample of 525 words, measuring both the overall accuracy of each system and how well that accuracy correlates (via mean square error) to the observed historical variation.
    Text mining; Perseus Project
  - Named Entity Identification and Cyberinfrastructure, 2007; PB.001.003.00001; Babeu, Alison; Bamman, David; Crane, Gregory; Kummer, Robert; Weaver, Gabriel
    Well-established instruments such as authority files and a growing set of data structures such as CIDOC CRM, FRBRoo, and MODS provide the foundation for emerging, new digital services. While solid, these instruments alone neither capture the essential data on which traditional scholarship depends nor enable the services which we can already identify as fundamental to any eResearch, cyberinfrastructure or virtual research environment for intellectual discourse. This paper describes a general model for primary sources, entities and thematic topics, the gap between this model and emerging infrastructure, and the tasks necessary to bridge it.
    Digital libraries; Cyberinfrastructure; Named entity recognition; FRBR (Conceptual model); CIDOC-CRM; MODS; FRBRoo; Metadata integration; Semantic classification; Perseus Project
  - Analyzing Human Systems Across Time, Space, Language, and Culture, 2011; PB.001.003.00002; Babeu, Alison; Crane, Gregory; Bamman, David; Cerrato, Lisa; Singhal, Rashmi
    Due to the rise of very large, heterogeneous collections, increasingly sophisticated multilingual services, and expanding high performance computing infrastructure, we are now in a position to begin studying 4000 years of linguistic data from around the world, tracing change within languages, the interaction of languages, the evolution and circulation of ideas, and the patterns of human society. Language has been an impenetrable barrier we can reach any point on the globe in a matter of hours but the amount of time required to master a new language remains unchanged. We can, however, now begin to work with far more languages than we could ever study, much less master. We are now in a position to pursue broader questions and to pursue these with greater rigor than would have been possible in print. A great deal of work remains to be done, however, for very large collections are not scientific corpora and need extensive processing, and many written sources do not yet lend themselves to optical character recognition. Simply scaling up existing systems to analyze millions of books poses software engineering challenges. Perhaps most important of all, we need to train a new generation of researchers who can bridge the intellectual gaps between the relevant computational methods and new research for social, behavioral and economic sciences.
  - Cataloging for a Billion Word Library of Greek and Latin, 2014; PB.001.003.00003; Babeu, Alison L.; Crane, Gregory.; Almas, Bridget.; Cerrato, Lisa.; Krohn, Anna.; Baumgart, Frederik.; Berti, Monica.; Franzini, Greta.; Stoyanova, Simona.; This paper reports work on a catalog that includes not only standard metadata but also a complete reference transcription for each work so that users can explicitly cite not only every version but also every word in every version of a work. The Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records conceptual model (FRBR) allows us to move beyond printed books and to track the logical units within (and often across) printed books: works (e.g., the Iliad) and expressions (e.g., versions such as the 10th century Venetus A manuscript or Butler's English translation). The Canonical Text Services (CTS) Data Model builds upon FRBR, allowing us to cite each word in any version of a text and to do so by building upon established citation schemes inherited from print (e.g., the chapter/verse citation scheme in the Bible). This paper describes a concrete implementation of such a catalogue of 3,679 Greek and Latin works that includes FRBR inspired metadata and TEI XML transcriptions that were revised to facilitate implementing a CTS API. It also describes how all the different versions of a work can be serialized as variations on the reference version. The FRBR+CTS catalog provides data by which text reuse and alignment services can automatically detect different versions of and quotations from the reference text, aligning all discovered instances according to a canonical citation scheme.
    Metadata.; FRBR (Conceptual model); Classical languages.; Tufts University. Department of Classics. Perseus Project
  - Spacing Out: Web 3D and the Reconstruction of Archaeological Sites, 2000; PB.001.004.00001; Milbank, Thomas L.
    The emergence of high-speed processors with 3D graphics acceleration and the accessibility of high-speed internet connections have propelled web 3D from a frustrating to a viable internet technology. Without a doubt, the addition of spatial dimension to customary 2D web graphics can be visually gripping. But greater potential for the technology lies beyond its ability to command attention. Web 3D presents students and scholars alike with a new tool for visualizing and understanding ancient sites. Fundamentally, 3D digital reconstruction allows architecture, sculpture, and other remains to be considered in their respective contexts as a whole, rather than as individual items divorced from their intended settings. At the same time, digital reconstruction can incorporate a distinction between the "real" and the "hypothetical" just as found in other types of modern restoration work. The Perseus Project is currently preparing 3D models of various archaeological sites. These will be linked to other related materials already in its digital library: maps; plans; photographs; QTVR walkthroughs; site, architecture, and object catalogs; and literary and historical documents. In part, the models are intended as databases of geographic and architectural information in their own right. They are also intended to serve as the underpinning for a contextual presentation of architectural and freestanding sculptures. This paper surveys Perseus' work on the Apollo sanctuary at Delphi. It addresses both the process of digital modeling and the method used to integrate the model with Perseus' existing tools and databases.
    XML (Document markup language); VRML (Computer program language); Archaeology; 3D graphic standards; Perseus Project
  - Extracting Geometry from Digital Models in a Cultural Heritage Digital Library, 2003; PB.001.004.00002; Milbank, Thomas L.
    This paper describes research to enhance the integration between digital models and the services provided by the document management systems of digital libraries. Processing techniques designed for XML texts are applied to X3D models, allowing specific geometry to be automatically retrieved and displayed. The research demonstrates that models designed on object-oriented paradigms are most easily exploited by XML document management system.
    XML (Document markup language); 3D graphic standards; Digital libraries; Perseus Project
  - Excavating the Hard Drive: Archaeological Research, XML, and 3D Graphics, 2003; PB.001.004.00003; Milbank, Thomas L.
    This paper focuses on the X3D XML application of the VRML international 3D graphic standard. It addresses the integration of X3D graphic files into the Perseus XML document management system. And it addresses the creation of a tool to extract and represent graphic elements from multiple files. The tool provides a specific research mechanism for the discovery of embedded graphic data interspersed through a large corpus, for example, allowing an archaeologist to retrieve every cornice from an extensive collection of files without having to open and search each file manually.
    XML (Document markup language); VRML (Computer program language); 3D graphic standards; Archaeology; Perseus Project
  - London calling: GIS, VR, and the Victorian period, 2001; PB.001.005.00001; Chavez, Robert F.; Milbank, Thomas L.
    The Bolles Collection of Tufts University represents a comprehensive and integrated collection of sources on the history and topography of Victorian London. Texts, images, maps, and three-dimensional reconstructions are all interconnected forming a body of material that transcends the limits of print publication and exploits the flexibility of the electronic medium. The Perseus Digital Library has incorporated Geographic Information System and Virtual Reality technologies in a set of tools intended to help readers synthesize and visualize the numerous temporal and spatial interconnections between Bolles Collection materials. The tools, which are applicable to any large assemblage of related documents, also help readers grasp the complex temporal-spatial interactions that shape historical materials in general.
    Cultural heritage; Digital libraries; VRML (Computer program language); Geographic information systems; Perseus Project
  - Generating and Reintegrating Geospatial Data, 2000; PB.001.005.00002; Chavez, Robert F.
    The process of building a geospatial component to access existing materials in the Perseus Digital Library has raised interesting questions about the interaction between historical and geospatial data. The traditional methods of describing geographic features' names and locations do not provide a complete solution for historical data such as that in the Perseus Digital Library. Very often data sources for a spatial database must be created from the historical materials themselves.
    Geographic information systems; Spatial data infrastructures; Data integration; Perseus Project
  - Services Make the Repository, 2006; PB.001.005.00003; Chavez, Robert F.; Crane, Gregory; Sauer, Anne; Jones, Alison; Weaver, Gabriel; Packel, Adrain
    This paper provides an overview of the collaboration between the Perseus Project and the Digital Collection and Archives at Tufts University in moving the collections of the Perseus Project into the DCA's Fedora based repository as well as a listing of potential services necessary to support a successful institutional repository.
    Institutional Repositories; Digital libraries; Fedora Commons; Perseus Project; Digital Collections and Archives
  - Detecting Events with Date and Place Information in Unstructured Text, 2002; PB.001.006.00001; Smith, David A.
    Digital libraries of historical documents provide a wealth of information about past events, often in unstructured form. Once dates and place names are identified and disambiguated, using methods that can differ by genre, we examine collocations to detect events. Collocations can be ranked by several measures, which vary in effectiveness according to type of events, but the log-likelihood measure offers a reasonable balance between frequently and infrequently mentioned events and between larger and smaller spatial and temporal ranges. Significant date-place collocations can be displayed on timelines and maps as an interface to digital libraries. More detailed displays can highlight key names and phrases associated with a given event.
    Event detection; Geographic name disambiguation; Visualization; Phrase browsing; Perseus Project
  - Detecting and Browsing Events in Unstructured Text, 2002; PB.001.006.00002; Smith, David A.
    Previews and overviews of large, heterogeneous information resources help users comprehend the scope of collections and focus on particular subsets of interest. For narrative documents, questions of \what happened? where? and when?" are natural points of entry. Building on our earlier work at the Perseus Project with detecting terms, place names, and dates, we have exploited co-occurrences of dates and place names to detect and describe likely events in document collections. We compare statistical measures for determining the relative significance of various events. We have built interfaces that help users preview likely regions of interest for a given range of space and time by plotting the distribution and relevance of various collocations. Users can also control the amount of collocation information in each view. Once particular collocations are selected, the system can identify key phrases associated with each possible event to organize browsing of the documents themselves.
    Visualization; Information extraction; Interactive information retrieval; Perseus Project
  - Disambiguating Geographic Names in a Historical Digital Library, 2001; PB.001.006.00003; Smith, David A.; Crane, Gregory
    Geographic interfaces provide natural, scalable visualizations for many digital library collections, but the wide range of data in digital libraries presents some particular problems for identifying and disambiguating place names. We describe the toponym-disambiguation system in the Perseus digital library and evaluate its performance. Name categorization varies significantly among different types of documents, but toponym disambiguation performs at a high level of precision and recall with a gazetteer an order of magnitude larger than most other applications.
    Digital libraries; Geographic name disambiguation; Names, Geographical; Gazetteers; Perseus Project
  - Management of XML Documents in an Integrated Digital Library, 2000; PB.001.006.00004; Smith, David A.; Mahoney, Anne; Rydberg-Cox, Jeffrey A.
    We describe a generalized toolset developed by the Perseus Pro ject to manage XML documents in the context of a large, heterogeneous digital library. The system manages multiple DTDs through mappings from elements in the DTD to abstract document structures. The abstraction of document metadata, both structural and descriptive, facilitates the development of application-level tools for knowledge management and document presentation. We discuss the implementation of the XML back end and describe applications for cross citation retrieval, toponym extraction and plotting, automatic hypertext generation, morphology, and word co-occurrence.
    Digital libraries; Document Type Definition (DTD); Automatic hypertext generation; Automatic linking; Knowledge management; Perseus Project
  - Integrating Harvesting into Digital Library Content, 2002; PB.001.006.00005; Smith, David A.; Mahoney, Anne; Crane, Gregory
    The Open Archives Initiative has gained success by aiming between complex federation schemes and low functionality web crawling. Much information still remains hidden inside documents catalogued by OAI metadata. We discuss how subdocument information can be exposed by data providers and exploited by service providers. We discuss services for citation reversal and name and term linking with harvested data in the Perseus Project's document management system and a proxy service for automatically adding these links to OAI documents outside Perseus.
    Digital libraries; Open Archives Initiative; OAI-PMH; Metadata harvesting; Perseus Project
  - Integrating data from The Perseus Project and Arachne using the CIDOC CRM: An Examination from a Software Developers Perspective, 2006; PB.001.007.00001; Kummer, Robert
    In a joint effort, The Perseus Project, a digital library hosted at Tufts University, and Arachne, the central database for archaeological objects of the German Archaeological Institute (DAI) and the Research Archive for Ancient Sculpture at the University of Cologne (FA), want to make their data accessible to a greater audience using the CIDOC CRM data model. Given the fact that the information in each of their databases is of interest to a large community of people, efforts to overcome the current lack of data integration have to be made. Aside from the philosophical implications and the mathematical background involved, the main concern of this project will be the practicability of a software implementation of all relevant concepts using basic Semantic Web technologies as described by the W3C, along with an investigation of the usability of the CIDOC CRM for a multilingual interface. The main purpose of the implementation process is to get a deeper understanding of the concepts and technologies involved when dealing with the Semantic Web, ontologies in general and the CIDOC CRM in particular. For the process of implementation it is essential that software tools team up with a methodical process, and that appropriate tools be discovered or developed and documented. Functional requirements have a tendency to evolve relatively rapidly when information systems are used by historians. Information systems in the humanities are especially confronted with the problem of constant change through the acquisition of new project partners carrying new and varied source material. As a consequence, potential integration efforts have to cope with changes of the database schemas and therefore should be flexible.
    CIDOC-CRM; Data integration; Ontologies (Information retrieval); Perseus Project
  - Managing Authority Lists for Customized Linking and Visualization: A Service for the National STEM Digital Library, 2002; PB.001.008.00001; Colati, Gregory
    We propose two broad classes of service to the NSDL. First, we will provide automatic linking services that automatically bind key words and phrases to supplementary information. Such automatic linking services are already in place in the Perseus Digital Library. These services will help students, professionals outside a particular discipline, and the interested public to read documents full of unfamiliar technical terms and concepts. Astronomy students and curious amateurs may need to see expansions of some acronyms, e.g., MACHO: massive compact halo object, such as neutron stars and brown dwarfs, or pictures of Kuiper belt objects. These services can be of particular help to undergraduates as they shift from textbooks to scientific literature: the student struggling with research papers on bioluminescence, for example, will be able to locate information about particular chemical processes or relevant species of echinoderms. Second, we will base automatic linking on authority control of names and terms and on links among different authority lists such as thesauri, glossaries, encyclopedias, subject hierarchies, and object catalogues.
    Digital libraries; Automatic linking; Perseus Project; National Science Digital Library
  - Vocabulary Building in the Perseus Digital Library, 2002; PB.001.009.00001; Rydberg-Cox, Jeffrey A.; Mahoney, Anne
    In this paper, we will describe a new computational tool in the Perseus Digital Library designed to help students learn vocabulary by generating Latin and Greek word lists that are tailored to reading assignments.
    Digital libraries; Customization; Vocabulary acquisition; Perseus Project
  - Collecting Fragmentary Authors in a Digital Library (Greek Fragmentary Historians), 2009; PB.001.010.00001; Berti, Monica; Romanello, Matteo; Babeu, Alison; Crane, Gregory